太长不看: 新冠疫情
COVID-19—that's the answer.
正是它导致了2020-2021年的各种短缺现象
That's what caused all the shortages of 2020 and 2021. That's it.
新冠导致全球商品短缺正如冰山导致泰坦尼克号沉没……
COVID-19 caused the shortages in the same way that an iceberg caused the Titanic to sink…
或者雷曼兄弟破产导致2008年全球金融危机……
or the collapse of Lehman Brothers caused the Great Recession…
或者最后一根稻草压垮了骆驼
or the straw broke the camel's back.
所以说 新冠的确导致了全球商品短缺——
That's really to say, COVID did cause these shortages—
如果没有疫情 全球也不会像现在这样啥啥都买不着
they would not have happened in the manner they did, when they did, if not for the pandemic.
但正如泰坦尼克号的设计缺陷终究会导致其沉没
But just as the Titanic's design flaws would eventually lead to calamity,
全球脆弱的经济模式早晚会导致金融危机
the vulnerabilities in the global economy would eventually lead to a recession,
总有一根稻草会压垮本已超载的骆驼一样
and something would eventually break the overloaded camel's back,
新冠疫情引发了全球短缺 但它不是根本原因
COVID caused these shortages, but it's not what made them possible.
根本原因来自于今天供应链运作方式中基础部分的结构性漏洞
What made them possible is a fundamental, structural vulnerability
in the way today's supply chains work.
2021年4月13日 加州都柏林的BB奶茶店在Facebook上发出公告
On April 13th, 2021, Boba Bliss, a small bubble tea shop in Dublin, California, posted on Facebook.
公告中提到由于他们近期原料供应困难
They explained that they were having a hard time getting their ingredients,
导致他们需要每天更新菜单——
and that this would mean their menu would have to change daily—
而这要根据他们每天能从供应商拿到哪些原料
reflective of what they could actually get from their supplier.
4月15日 纽约卡南达瓜的MTB奶茶店
On April 15th, MighTea Boba, in Canandaigua, New York
也在Facebook上宣布将减少每杯奶茶中的珍珠量
explained on Facebook that they would have to serve a smaller quantity of tapioca pearls in each drink,
且不再提供额外加珍珠的选项——同样是原料供应短缺导致的
and would no longer be offering extra as an option, due to a shortage of this ingredient.
亚利桑那州图森的BBT奶茶店也在一周后发布了同样的内容
Bing's Boba Tea in Tucson, Arizona said much the same one week later,
随后是加州旧金山的TH奶茶店
and Tea Hut in San Francisco, California
他们宣布因原料涨价 商品价格也要提高26%
then announced that they would have to raise their prices due to a 26% rise in their ingredient costs.
虽然奶茶的需求量没有急剧增加
All across the country, shops selling this popular Taiwanese drink
但全美各地卖这款中国台湾特色饮品的商店都进不来原料了
simply could not get ingredients in the quantities demanded, despite no dramatic increase in demand.
然而在珍珠奶茶里珍珠的主要产地——大洋彼岸的中国台湾
However, thousands of miles away, in Taiwan, where much of the world's Bubble Tea ingredients are made,
一切却正常得多
things were operating fairly normally.
在全球疫情肆虐的时候 台湾省每日确诊只有个位数
With single-digit daily case numbers for much of COVID's reign,
岛上的工厂完全可以全负荷运转 这在世界其他地方是做不到的
factories on the island were able to work at full-force in a way they couldn't elsewhere.
可事实是 BB MTB BBT TH奶茶店等全美上千家奶茶店都拿不到原料
But still, somehow, Boba Bliss, MighTea Boba, Bing's Boba Tea, Tea Hut,
and thousands of other shops across the US couldn't get their product.
背后的原因其实跟台湾没啥关系
The problem had less to do with anything happening in Taiwan,
主要原因其实藏在洛杉矶港口外的海面上
and more with what happening here— in the waters off the coast of Los Angeles.
在2021年的上半年
Throughout the first half of 2021,
几十艘货轮挨个在太平洋的天际线上搁那站岗
a rotating cast of dozens of cargo ships have dotted the Pacific's horizon.
锚一抛 一停就是几个礼拜
Each sat there, at anchor, sometimes for weeks,
直到洛杉矶或长滩港有一个空余的位置
until a spot opened for them at the port of Los Angeles or Long Beach.
这很反常
This is abnormal.
虽然前一年可能有那么一两艘船需要等待一两天
While the year prior it was possible for a ship or two to have to wait a day or two,
但从来没有过几十艘船一等就是几十天这样的情况
it was never dozens of ships for dozens of days.
台湾到洛杉矶的运输时间通常是两周左右
Transit time from Taiwan to Los Angeles typically takes about two weeks,
所以再在港口外等十多天 意味着运输时间就要翻倍
so an additional ten days of waiting represents a near doubling of shipping times.
当然 造成这种情况的根本原因来自于疫情触发的连锁反应
The root cause of this was, of course, a perfect, pandemic-fueled storm.
随着2020年节假日的临近 美国有越来越多的人开始复工复产
As the 2020 holiday season approached, more people were getting back to work in the US,
消费也在复苏 网购也在爆炸性增长
consumer spending was ticking up, and online shopping was exploding.
由于旅游 餐饮 演出和其他服务的机会有限
With limited access to travel, restaurants, shows, and other services,
实体产品是人们可以自由支配收入的少数途径之一
physical products were one of the few ways people could spend their discretionary income.
越来越多的商品从亚洲的工厂运来
More goods than ever were coming from factories in Asia,
而美国49.1%的商品是通过两大港口之一——洛杉矶和长滩进口的
and 49.1% of those imports to the US passed through one of just two ports—Los Angeles and Long Beach.
与一年前 新冠疫情重创美国之前那段时间相比
Compared to a year prior, before COVID hit the US in earnest,
在2021年2月 这两个港口的船舶和集装箱运输量分别增加了31%和49%
February 2021 saw a 31% increase in ships and a 49% increase in container traffic at these two ports.
他们应付不过来了
They just couldn't keep up.
然而与此同时 有相当一部分港口工人还会因防疫条例或者确诊而缺席
Simultaneously, however, a significant tranche of dock-workers
were constantly out sick due to COVID itself or the quarantine procedures it demanded.
这还不算完
But the disorder doesn't end there.
去年20尺集装箱大约需要1800美元 而现在则需要3500美元
While a year ago a 20-foot container would cost about $1,800, they now run for $3,500.
区域性的集装箱短缺带来的是全球性的影响
There's a regional shortage of shipping containers that's having global consequences.
在2020年 全球其他地方都进入封锁状态的时候
You see, in 2020, just as much of the world entered lockdowns,
中国的制造业正稳步复苏
China's manufacturing industry was emerging from it.
全世界都在从中国购买口罩 个人防疫用品和常规的商品
The entire world bought masks, personal protective equipment, and regular goods from the country
而等这些集装箱抵达长滩等港口 它们就会被卸下
and once those containers arrived in ports like Long Beach, they were unloaded.
然而由于那些目的地国家的封锁状态
However, due to those destination country's lockdowns,
他们并没有多少东西需要对外出口
there wasn't really much that needed to be shipped out.
每100个进口到美国的集装箱 只有40个会被出口
For every 100 containers that are imported into the US, only 40 are exported.
因此 大量空集装箱就这样白白占着茅坑
So, containers stacked up in the places there weren't needed, because they weren't needed,
也没法运回它们的出发地 比如亚洲
and they didn't make it back to the places where they were, like Asia.
就洛杉矶港和长滩港而言
In the case of the ports of Los Angeles and Long Beach,
他们处理进口货物能力的紧张意味着
their capacity crunch means
他们甚至没时间去实践验证空集装箱装船返回亚洲是可行的
they don't even have the time to justify loading ships with empty containers for return to Asia.
不仅如此 美国卡车司机的短缺
Not only that, but a shortage of truck drivers in the US
也意味着将空的集装箱从目的地运回港口再送回亚洲是不现实的
means that it's tough to actually get empty containers
back from their final destinations to ports to send them back to Asia.
因此 海运集装箱的短缺加剧了海运能力的不足
So, a shortage a shipping containers is worsening a shortage of shipping capacity,
而港口处理能力的不足又加剧了集装箱的短缺 从而加剧了海运能力的不足
which is worsened by a shortage of port capacity, which is worsening the shortage of shipping containers,
而卡车司机的短缺又让情况雪上加霜
which itself is worsened by a shortage of truck drivers,
这一切导致珍珠奶茶没有了珍珠
all of which is causing a shortage of bubble tea ingredients.
A短缺导致B短缺 从而引起C短缺——
Shortages causing shortages causing shortages—
这样的恶性循环随着经济的重新开放只会越来越糟
it's a vicious cycle that is only worsening as economies reopen.
在全世界 这样的短缺状况层出不穷
Across the world, there's a proliferation of scarcity.
美国的木材价格本来预测说要降 结果翻了两番
Lumber prices in the US quadrupled after predicted decline failed to manifest,
而建筑和装修行业反而因此繁荣起来
and a boom in construction and renovation did instead.
游泳池的使用和建造产业也加速了
The use and construction of pools also accelerated,
因为户外空间变得越来越宝贵 刺激了对氯气的需求
as outdoor space became more valuable, spurring increased demand for chlorine
再加上路易斯安那州一家大型氯气工厂火灾导致供应减少
which, when mixed with reduced supply as a result of a fire at a major chlorine plant in Louisiana,
引发了产品短缺与价格飞涨
led to sky-high prices, and insufficient availability.
随着餐馆转型打包和外卖
As restaurants pivoted to take-out and delivery,
散装番茄酱消失了 单份小包的番茄酱开始出现
bulk ketchup was out, and single-serve packets were in,
但由于制造商不愿意花费大量资金来增加短期内的生产能力
but with manufacturers unwilling to spend significantly
to increase production capacity for a short-term bump,
小包番茄酱变得稀缺 在eBay上10美元50份的价格都有不少人买
the packets became scarce, and companies started successfully selling them for $10 per 50 on eBay.
而最大的短缺问题则发生在阿拉斯加安克雷奇机场外空荡荡的停车场里
However, the greatest shortage of all can be seen here,
in the empty parking lots of Anchorage, Alaska's airport.
阿拉斯加州严重依赖夏季的旅游高峰
The state relies heavily on its summer tourism season,
他们错过了去年的旅游高峰 所以2021年的夏季至关重要
and after missing it last year, 2021's season is crucial.
面对5月前运营合法性的不确定性
Facing uncertainty about the legality of their operation until May,
游轮公司取消了许多前往阿拉斯加的夏季航线
cruise companies cancelled many of their summer sailings to Alaska,
所以今年都是独立出行的美国国内游客
so this year is all about independent, domestic tourists.
想要穿越阿拉斯加州的广阔荒野 独立旅行者需要租赁汽车
To traverse the vast wilderness of the last frontier, independent travelers need rental cars.
然而 这些游客却租不到车——
However, these travelers can't get rental cars—
无论你在2021年夏季的哪一天 都完全租不到车
regardless of which date you search in summer 2021, there simply isn't availability.
对于少数找到车的幸运儿 面对的也是一辆小型汽车每日500美元以上的天价
For the lucky few who do find one, current market rates are over $500 a day for a compact car.
美国人现在可以《合法》《安全》《轻松》地前往阿拉斯加旅行
American travelers can now legally, safely, and easily get to Alaska,
但到了以后州里哪都去不成 所以他们根本不会成行
but they can't get around Alaska, which means that eager travelers aren't going.
在美国疫情最水深火热的时期
You see, during the depths of the pandemic,
H E N和其它很多租车公司都卖掉了他们的车
Hertz, Enterprise, National, and other rental car companies sold off much of their fleets of cars—
因为租车行业赚不到钱 而他们又需要钱
they needed money somehow, and it wasn't coming from rentals themselves.
而现在 随着美国所有人都可以轻易地接种疫苗
Now, however, with vaccinations easily available to all in the US,
租车的需求上来了 但车辆供应没了
there is demand for rentals, yet no supply.
特别是在阿拉斯加 由于当地高度季节性的旅游市场
In Alaska especially, with its highly seasonal tourism market,
租车公司通常会在秋季卖掉他们的旧车
it's normal for the rental car companies to sell off their old vehicles in the fall,
再在春季买入新车
and purchase new ones in spring,
但今年 后半部分剧情没加载出来
but the latter half of that didn't happen this year,
因为全球大规模汽车短缺
because there's a massive, global shortage of new cars,
制造商根本无法满足租车公司的大量订单
and manufacturers are simply unable to fulfill the huge orders rental car companies are asking for.
随着疫情在2020年春天蔓延全球
You see, in Spring, 2020, as COVID took hold of the globe,
汽车制造商取消或减少了他们的部件订单
car manufacturers canceled and reduced their orders for components
因为他们预计新车的需求会减少
as they anticipated reduced demand for new vehicles.
预测的没错 需求确实下降了 因为经济衰退期间需求都会下降
They were right on that—demand did go down as it tends to during any recession—
但它恢复得比任何人想象的都快
but it recovered faster than anyone imagined.
总之 他们的计划是
Regardless, the plan was that,
等经济复苏开始 他们就增加部件订单并逐步开始制造
once recovery started, they'd boost component orders and manufacturing in step.
但问题是 他们来晚了
The problem was that they're now at the back of the line,
等着购买汽车上一个关键零件的队伍可老长了
and for one, critical component of modern automobiles, there's quite a long line.
计算机芯片到处都卖光了
Computer chips are sold out everywhere.
这是一场完美的蝴蝶效应
It was the perfect storm of circumstances.
首先 中美贸易战使中国制造商开始囤积芯片
First, the US' trade war with China caused the country's manufacturers to start stockpiling the chips.
然后 新冠疫情导致世界上一些地区生产停滞
Then, COVID led to production shutdowns in certain areas of the world,
人们更多时间待在家中 对消费电子产品的需求剧增
demand for consumer electronics exploded as people spent more time at home,
现在甚至连解决方案本身都会加剧这样的困境
and now, even the solution is causing problems
因为计算机芯片和疫苗瓶都需要硅
as silicon is both needed in computer chips and vaccine vials.
总之 原因很复杂 但结果很明显:
Altogether, the reasons are complex, but the result is clear:
大家抢不到PS5了
this is why you still can't easily buy a PS5,
三星今年不出新Galaxy系列手机了
this is why Samsung likely won't release a new Galaxy smartphone this year,
阿拉斯加租不到车了
and this is why you can't get a rental car in Alaska.
而一个残酷的讽刺是 汽车行业对这一切都负有责任
In a twist of cruel irony, the car industry is culpable for all of this.
这是因为几十年前 这个现在受苦最深的行业
That's because, decades ago, the very industry that is now suffering the hardest
搞出了一套生产系统 使这种短缺成为可能
propagated a system that made shortages such as this so possible.
80年前 日本从二战中复苏时 丰田遇到了一个问题
Eighty years ago, as Japan emerged from World War Two, Toyota had a problem.
世界正朝着进一步全球化的方向发展
The world was marching towards further globalization,
特别是日本开始与美国建立贸易关系
and Japan especially was starting to develop a trade relationship with the US.
不过当时的美国汽车制造商相比日本同行有巨大的成本优势
American car manufacturers, at the time, though, had a huge cost edge over their Japanese counterparts.
特别是在战后经济繁荣 对汽车需求如此之高的时期
Especially during the post-war economic boom, demand for their vehicles was so high
以至于美国制造商在当时拥有相当巨大的规模效应
that American manufacturers had incredible economies of scale.
他们的流程是批量制造——
Their process was batch manufacturing—
在特定的时间 特定的装配线专门制造一种类型一种型号的车辆
at a given time, a given assembly line would build one type of one model of one vehicle, exclusively.
然后他们会切换到另一种型号另一种类型 如此循环往复
Then, they'd switch to another type of another model, and so on and so forth.
借此 制造商可以使用大规模的生产线 以极快的速度工作
With this, the manufacturers could use massive production lines working at breakneck pace,
但丰田不一样
unlike Toyota's.
他们的生产线又小又慢
Theirs were small and slow.
日本国内的汽车市场有限 但又有相当多的车辆类型需求
The domestic car market in Japan was limited, and it demanded quite a lot of variety in vehicle types.
这意味着他们没有足够的经济规模来进行批量制造——
This meant that they didn't have the scale to make batch manufacturing work well—
至少没法搞得像美国那样好
at least as well as in the US.
他们无法达到批量生产的收益
Their inability to realize the gains of batch manufacturing
意味着与他们新的美国竞争对手相比 自己必须有更高的价格
meant that they simply would have to have higher prices compared to their new American competitors,
在当时也没有一个明确的替代方案
but there just wasn't a clear alternative.
所以他们自己创造了一个
So, they created one.
他们创造了丰田生产系统
They created the Toyota Production System.
它有两个核心原则 首先是"自働化"——不是"自动化" 是"自働化"
It had two core principles, starting with autonomation—not automation, autonomation.
这是他们对有效利用自动化的说法
This was their term for the efficient use of automation.
现在 完全的自动化不但需要机器来制造汽车
Now, complete automation would require machines to build cars,
还要能够诊断任何问题 并修复这些问题
plus diagnose any problems, plus fix those problems,
但让机器自己修复问题是非常复杂非常昂贵的
but having machines fix their own problems is very complicated and very expensive.
因此 在他们的自働化系统中 他们只寻找机器能比人类做得更好的地方
So, in their autonomation system, they look for only what machines can do better than humans,
对于他们来说 主要是车辆组装的工作和问题的诊断
which in their context was most of vehicle assembly and problem diagnosis,
而问题的解决则留给人类
while problem-solving was left to humans.
自働化从过去到现在一直都是丰田生产系统的一个关键组成部分
Autonomation was and still is a crucial, critical component of the Toyota Production System,
但系统本身并没有从根本上改变制造业的核心原则
but it wasn't the core principle that would go on to change manufacturing fundamentally.
起到作用的是"精益生产"原则
What did was the principle of just-in-time manufacturing.
它实际上是这样的:
All it really is is this:
制造过程中的每一个步骤都应该在下一个步骤准备开始时结束
each step in the manufacturing process should end when the next one is ready to start.
这是一个推动系统 与之对应的是拉动系统
It's a pull system, as opposed to a push system.
就好比咖啡厅在顾客来之前不会自己搁那玩手冲
Just as your Coffee shop doesn't start making your latte until you ask for it,
PVB只有在夹层安全玻璃生产设施准备好制造挡风玻璃时才会生产出厂
the polyvinyl butyral resin should only leave the chemicals plant
when the laminated safety glass production facility is ready to start making windshields,
且只有在总装配线准备好将所有部件总装起来时才会开始制造挡风玻璃
and it should only start making windshields
when the final assembly line is ready to put all the pieces together,
且只有在经销商准备好停放新车的地方时才会开启总装线
and it should only start putting all the pieces together
when the dealership is ready to put more cars on its lot.
在丰田生产系统眼里 过剩的库存就是浪费
In the view of the Toyota Production System, excess inventory is waste,
因为持有库存花钱不赚钱
because holding inventory costs money without making money.
消除多余的库存就是消除浪费
Elimination of excess inventory is elimination of waste,
而消除浪费就能提高生产效率
and elimination of waste is what leads to production efficiency.
这套系统很有用
This system worked.
在20世纪50年代初 丰田公司处于破产的边缘
In the early 1950's, Toyota was on the brink of bankruptcy.
而到了今天 该公司是世界上最大的汽车制造商
Today, the company is the largest auto manufacturer in the world,
丰田生产系统的原理也早已写进了商界的教科书中
and the principles of the Toyota Production System can be found in any business textbook.
精益生产不再是一种创新 而是一种规范
Just-in-time manufacturing is no longer an innovation—it's the norm.
文章中没有写到实施精益生产的公司 反而只写了那些没有实施的公司
Articles aren't written about companies implementing just-in-time—they're written about those that don't.
事实上 精益生产在今天已经变得更加不可或缺
In fact, just-in-time has become even more integral today.
如果一个制造过程有六个步骤 而每个步骤积压了两个月的库存
If there are six steps in a manufacturing process and each holds two months of inventory,
那么就需要一年的时间来转向生产一个新产品
it would take a year to pivot to producing a new product.
这对于当今生命周期极短的科技行业产品是完全不可接受的
The short product life-cycles of today's technology industry would not accept that.
精益生产这条原则看上去简单
Just-in-time is such a simple principle,
但当今追求消除浪费已经是任何大型制造商的首要任务
but the pursuit of the elimination of waste is now the central mission of any major manufacturer.
然而 他们大多数都搞错了
However, most did it wrong.
全球制造商都只看到了表面的好处——消除库存带来的巨大效率提升——
Manufacturers globally saw the headline—elimination of inventory leads to massive efficiency gains—
就盲目去搞精益生产 却忽视了它盘活丰田的根本原因
and jumped on that, without actually determining what made it work for Toyota.
他们忽略了日本较小的市场规模使得国内供应链较短
They ignored that Japan's small physical size made for short domestic supply chains,
容错率更高
less vulnerable to things going wrong.
他们忽略了公司的生产平衡——
They ignored the company's production leveling—
找到平均每日需求量并进行生产 而并不需要考虑需求的短期变化
finding the average daily demand and producing that, regardless of short-term changes in demand.
他们忽视了"消除过剩库存"与"消除所有库存"不同的事实
They ignored the fact that eliminating excess inventory is different from eliminating all inventory.
他们忽视了培养跨职能工人组成的强大团队的基本原则——对人的尊重
They ignored the principle of growing strong teams of cross-functional workers,
predicted on respecting people.
他们忽视了原本停手解决问题 尝试第一次就把事情做好的文化
They ignored the culture of stopping and fixing problems, to get things right the first time.
他们忽视了丰田之道的大部分内容 创造了一个效率和容错性都更低的系统
They ignored huge swaths of the Toyota Way and created a system that's less effective and less resilient,
换来的只有通过短期的节约哄股东开心
but can impress shareholders through short-term savings.
丰田这套生产系统是一本厚厚的教科书 但有的人只看了封面就说自己学会了
How Toyota has effectively implemented this system fills books, but many are just reading the covers.
甚至丰田自己都没整明白
Even Toyota, though, is not perfect.
2011年日本发生了9.0级的地震——
In 2011, Japan was rocked by a 9.0 magnitude earthquake—
这是有记录以来第四强的地震
the fourth strongest ever recorded anywhere.
这不仅给生命和财产造成了巨大的破坏
Not only did this cause immense destruction to life and property,
也让丰田认识到了自己生产系统中的缺陷
but it also led Toyota to recognize a flaw in its own system.
在日本的重建工作中 一些供应链也迅速恢复——
As Japan recovered, some supply chains were quick to as well—
例如用于车门的密封树脂并不难搞到
for example, securing plastic resin for door panel production is not difficult.
全世界有无数家生产商有各种各样的替代品
There are plenty of manufacturers globally creating easily substitutable alternatives.
但半导体行业不是这样
That's not the case with, say, semiconductors.
生产芯片设备极其昂贵 需要多年的时间来建造
The hugely expensive facilities that create these chips require years to construct,
在2011年的地震之后 人们花了数月时间才将它们恢复到正常运行状态
and after the 2011 earthquake, it took many months to mend them back to operating status.
这展现了一个之前很少充分考虑到的事实——
This surfaced a truth that had never been fully considered—
并非所有的供应链都是平等的
not all supply chains are made equal.
密封树脂供应链断了很好解决
Plastic resin can handle supply chain disruption.
但半导体可做不到
Semiconductors cannot.
因此 丰田做出了改变
Therefore, Toyota made changes.
一直以来 他们的任务都不是全面消除库存
All along, their mission was not to eliminate inventory full-stop—
而是消除多余的库存
it was to eliminate excess inventory.
供应链中断是不可避免的
Supply chain disruption is inevitable.
就好设计有缺陷的泰坦尼克号早晚有一天会撞到冰山
It's inevitable in the same way that Titanic flawed design would eventually encounter an iceberg
或者2008年全球经济的结构性漏洞迟早会闹出金融危机一样
or the structural economic vulnerabilities of 2008 would eventually collide with a market panic.
因此 半导体的库存永远不会过剩
Therefore, semiconductor inventory is not excess because inevitably,
因为供应链危机无法避免
due to the inevitability of disruption,
所以多余的库存总会在危急时刻派上用场
excess semiconductor inventory will eventually become necessary.
认识到这一点后 丰田公司在最近几年
Recognizing this, Toyota, in recent years,
开始囤积了够自己用两到六个月的芯片库存
has started to build up a stockpile of two to six months worth of chips,
也因此该公司是唯一不受半导体短缺影响的大型汽车制造商
and that's why the company is the only major vehicle manufacturer that is unfazed
by the semiconductor shortage.
丰田一直恪守自己的准则
Toyota followed its own principles.
没有背离 也没有改变
It did not stray from them, and it did not reinvent them.
丰田实施自家生产系统表现出色倒并不奇怪
It's no surprise that Toyota excels at implementing its own system,
但整个制造业能如此处心积虑地盲目追求有缺陷的版本实在说不过去
but it is a surprise that the entire manufacturing world
has so wholeheartedly embraced flawed implementation of the system.
因为现实情况是精益生产的效率更高
The reality is that just-in-time manufacturing is more efficient,
而有些人认为 这种效率必须以牺牲容错性为代价
but some think that that efficiency must come with a trade-off in resilience.
但这也不对
That's simply not true.
适当的精益生产制供应链一旦形成 其本质自然是零弹性的
Proper just-in-time supply chains must inherently be inflexible once formed,
但其呈现形式却是灵活的
but their form is flexible.
这是哲学 不是死板的公式
It's a philosophy, not an equation.
经济中的短缺问题是非常复杂的 其任何解释都是高度简化的
Shortages in an economy are incredibly complex, and any explanation of them is an oversimplification,
但精益生产不一定就是背后唯一的罪魁祸首
but just-in-time manufacturing does not have to be the cause.
同样 供应链中断也是无法避免的 也不可能成为原因
In addition, disruption is inevitable, so it can't be the cause.
你不能把房子被淹这件事归咎于你把它盖在海里了
You can't blame the fact that your house is sinking on the fact that you built it in the ocean.
厂商牺牲长期利益为代价 盲目追求短期利润才是原因
A ruthless pursuit of short-term profit at the expense of long-term gain is the cause.
尽可能贴近短期利润的极限 的确是最高效的生产方式
Running as close as possible to the edge is the most efficient manner to manufacture,
直到供应链崩溃
until it isn't.
构建一个有弹性的供应链需要从长计议
Constructing a resilient supply chain requires long-term thinking,
但大多数公司没有培养出一个允许这样做的环境
but most companies have not nurtured an environment that allows for that.
随着世界从疫情中恢复过来 许多公司将放弃他们自己所谓的精益生产
As the world recovers from the pandemic, many will ditch what they call just-in-time manufacturing,
因为他们需要接受这些公司的负责人没有正确践行精益生产制
as the alternative is to accept that the very people in charge of those companies
have't implemented it properly.
说实话 能做到的公司很少 甚至丰田都还在学习更好地实践自己的生产系统
To be fair, few have, and even Toyota is still learning how to best implement its own system.
不过丰田已经证明 只要恪守原则
However, Toyota has proven that strict adherence to its principles
如果能清晰认识到什么是"过剩" 那么精益生产就能高效与弹性多方面兼顾
means just-in-time manufacturing can be everything at once—
it can be both efficient and resilient, if one knows what is truly excess.
正确实施丰田生产系统不会解决所有的短缺问题
Proper implementation of the Toyota system won't fix every shortage
但的确可以为一家公司解决一个短缺问题
but it did fix one shortage for one company.
因此 如果汽车行业能做好关键部件的库存管理
Therefore, if the auto industry had built a stockpile of critical components,
如果能更严格地调整生产平衡
if it had implemented production leveling more strictly,
如果能多了解一下进出口供应链的脆弱性
and if it had understood vulnerabilities in inbound supply chains,
那阿拉斯加可能就不会一车难租了吧
Alaska would have its rental cars.